All righty, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is נ"ז Nun
Zayin officially. We're on נ"ו עמוד ב'. Nun Vav Amud Bet. We're
going to make a very serious effort and see if we can
catch up. We pick up at the top of נ"ו עמוד ב',
Nun Vav Amud Bet, where it says,
והרי החמורים, ve-harei ha-chamorim, the donkey drivers, four lines from the top.
And the issue had been that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows a
woman to be מוחל mochel a part of the כתובה, kesuvah, so
effectively the כתובה kesuvah is less than 200 or 100, but he
doesn't allow an initial stipulation for it to start as less than
that. And that's the גמרא Gemara says why not? He says that
you could even be מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה, masneh al mah
she-kasuv ba-Torah, you can even change the parameters of the monetary aspects
of the biblical obligations of the קידושין, kiddushin, שאר כסות ועונה. she'er
kesut ve-onah. So how could he not allow you to change the
rabbinic? And his basic answer is that the rabbis wanted to strengthen
the rabbinic institution of כתובה, kesuvah, עשו חיזוק לדבריהם יותר משל תורה.
asu chizuk le-divreihem yoter mi-shel Torah. So they wanted to prevent that
from being modified even if you could modify some of the biblical
monetary obligations. So now the גמרא Gemara says the following: הרי חמורים,
harei chamorim, but one minute, there's the case of the donkey drivers,
דשכיחי, de-shchichei, which is a common scenario because we said also that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was only going to strengthen כתובה kesuvah which
was common, ולא עבדו בה רבנן חיזוק. ve-lo avdu ba-rabbanan chizuk. And
the rabbis didn't reinforce it. Now, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah,
חמורים שנכנסו לעיר, chamorim she-nichnesu le-ir, donkey drivers come to the city,
actually they're also like merchants. ואמר אחד מהן, ve-amar echad me-hen, and
one says, שלי חדש ושל חברי ישן. sheli chadash ve-shel chaveiri yashan.
We had this before. My grain is new grain, and this does
not mean because we're going to say this is all rabbinic issues,
so this does not mean the biblical aspects of חדש, chadash, but
it means just it's new and therefore new is not as good,
it hasn't been as dried out. So mine is of inferior quality
and my friend's here is old. שלי אינו מתוקן ושל חברי מתוקן,
sheli eino metukan ve-shel chaveiri metukan, mine does not have תרומות ומעשרות
terumot u-ma'asrot separated from it and my friend's does. אינו נאמן, eino
ne'eman, they're not believed, even though you would say look, he's saying
buy from my friend don't buy from me, maybe that should give
us weight to believe him. But no, the point is in this
city this is what they say and in the next city they
reverse it, so maybe they've got a whole trick going on here.
רבי יהודה אומר נאמנים, Rabbi Yehuda omer ne'emanim, they are believed. So
why is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda prepared to believe them? It's an
issue of דמאי, demai, rabbinically we have to be concerned that the
עמי הארץ amei ha-aretz have not taken תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u-ma'asrot. Why
doesn't he try to protect this rabbinic institution? Now of course it's
a little bit different, I mean we were dealing with cases about
institutions that created monetary obligations and to say that he didn't want
us to mess with them. This is a question about an obligation
to take תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot and who can you believe and
so on, not exactly the same. Just because he wants to strengthen
financial obligations that the rabbis instituted doesn't mean he's going to come
to the defense of every single rabbinic institution. But nevertheless that's the
גמרא's Gemara question. So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
אמר אביי ודאי דדבריהם עבדו רבנן חיזוק ספק דדבריהם לא עבדו רבנן
חיזוק.
amar Abaye vadai de-divreihem
avdu rabbanan chizuk safek de-divreihem lo avdu rabbanan chizuk.
No,
something that was a definite institution like the obligations of the כתובה,
kesuvah, the rabbis reinforced and said that you can't modify them at
least directly, you can only indirectly modify them by being מוחל. mochel.
Something that of taking תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot by דמאי, demai, that
yes it's a rabbinic institution but it's because of a doubt, it's
because of a
doubt maybe תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot weren't taken and therefore since the
whole thing is based on a question it's weaker fundamentally and he
did not want to bother reinforcing it. רבא אמר דמאי הקילו. Rava
amar demai hikilu. Rava says it's not just a general thing that's
based on a doubt, specifically it's דמאי demai and דמאי demai there
are lots of leniencies because by דמאי demai in principle we really
believe that תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot were taken so therefore we are
going to have lots of leniencies by דמאי. demai. Bottom line is
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows you is not as strict as
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't even allow the
woman to be מוחל mochel part of the כתובה, kesuvah, the effective
obligation for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir has to be 200 and 100.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows a woman to be מוחל mochel but
doesn't allow the amount to be modified at the outset
because even though he allows a person to modify biblical monetary obligations
of the marriage, this rabbinic one he wants to reinforce and therefore
the base obligation has to be there, you have to start with
the 200 and the 100 even if afterwards then the woman could
be מוחל. mochel. Now we have, so that was רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, now we go back to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, I've been
saying רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir first, anyway here's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
in the משנה. Mishnah. רבי מאיר אומר כל הפוחת, Rabbi Meir omer
kol ha-pocheis, anybody who has less than 200 for the בתולה betulah
and 100 for the אלמנה almanah is בעילת זנות. be'ilat zenut.
Now you and I might have thought that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
was saying that you can't effectively make the obligation less, but you
will transgress to continue to live in that marital state is considered
like בעילת זנות, be'ilat zenut, it doesn't have. of the safeguards of
marriage and therefore it is more, it's more like fornication than it
is like marriage. Marriage has something that comes, the whole idea of
the כתובה, Ksuva, the whole idea of this מסכת Masechet of נישואין,
Nisuin, of what gives it the weight is the fact that it
has all of these reciprocal obligations and all of these protections. So
the simple sense of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is that you have
effectively lowered the amount, but it just, it just doesn't, but then
you transgress.
The גמרא Gemara is actually going to take this one step further
and
argue that you don't even manage succeed in lowering the amount according
to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Let's take a look. כל הפוחת Kol
hapoches says the גמרא, Gemara, אפילו בתנאי, afilu bitnai, even if you
do it with a, even if you explicitly try to stipulate that
it should be less. אלמא קסבר תנאי בטל. Alma kasavar tnai batel.
So it seems that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that that stipulation
is void. Again, not clear, there's a long תוספות Tosfos now here
when this came up earlier that tries to figure out how the
גמרא Gemara knows that, but somehow the גמרא Gemara assumes that for
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, he's not just saying
that
you are transgressing, but he's actually saying that the stipulation to make
it less is void and you haven't actually succeeded in making it
less. Okay, maybe because it's in the כל הפוחת, Kol hapoches, somebody
who's attempting to be reduced the amount, but you don't actually succeed,
but even that attempt makes it ביאת זנות. bi'as znus. So the
גמרא Gemara says אלמא קסבר תנאי בטל ואית לה, alma kasavar tnai
batel ve'is lah, she still gets the full amount, you just attempted
to make it less. וכיון דאמר לה, Vekivan de'amar lah, so then
how is it ביאת זנות bi'as znus if it's still the full
amount? Because since the husband said to her, לית לך, lays lich,
you don't have 200, you only have 100, אלא מנה, ella mane,
you only have 100. לא סמכא דעתה, Lo samcha da'atah, so even
though in principle she has 200, since she thinks that she only
has 100, that subjective sense that she doesn't have the protections even
though it's not in true and fact is enough to create ביאת
זנות. bi'as znus. והויא לה בעילתו בעילת זנות, Vehavya lah bilato bilas
znus,
and that's ביאת זנות. bi'as znus. So the גמרא's Gemara first big
חידוש, chidush, which is question, not clear how it got it from
the משנה, Mishnah, is that the תנאי tnai is בטל, batel, which
isn't clear, so the woman has the full amount, and then the
second part of that is that even though she has the full
amount, it's still ביאת זנות bi'as znus because she thinks she does
it. Now the גמרא Gemara wants to understand why is this condition
בטל. batel. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: והא שמעינא ליה
Veha shama'ina leh לרבי מאיר leRabbi Meir דאמר כל המתנה על מה
שכתוב בתורה תנאו בטל. de'amar kol hamasneh al mah shekasuv baTorah tna'o
batel. Don't we hear, didn't we know, don't we know that רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says that if you try to stipulate against a
תורה Torah obligation, even a financial one, the condition is בטל? batel?
הא בדרבנן תנאו קיים, Habderabanan tna'o kayam, and the גמרא Gemara assumes
that he specifically meant a biblical obligation. If you stipulate against a
rabbinic obligation, it's actually binding. So why can't you stipulate against the
כתובה? Ksuva? Can't you stipulate for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir against a
rabbinic monetary obligation?
So you could have said, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is reinforcing the
כתובה. Ksuva. It's different if he wants to protect it more than
other rabbinic obligations.
It's about marriage and ביאת זנות bi'as znus and so on. But
the גמרא Gemara rather than making כתובה Ksuva unique or making it
in that way says the following: קסבר רבי מאיר כתובה דאורייתא. Kasavar
Rabbi Meir Ksuva de'oraisa. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir maybe actually holds that
כתובה Ksuva is biblical, we had that debate earlier, and therefore you
cannot stipulate against it. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara is very מחודש.
mechudash. רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, all he seems to be saying is
that you might succeed in changing the amount, but you are transgressing
by doing so, and maybe every day you continue to live together
that way you're transgressing. The גמרא Gemara changes רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
to say that the attempt to change the amount does not succeed.
Why not? Because it's מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה masneh al mah
shekasuv baTorah and כתובה's Ksuva דאורייתא. de'oraisa. Okay, that's also a חידוש.
chidush. You could have just said that maybe he protects the כתובה
Ksuva institution, but the גמרא Gemara made it specifically because כתובה's Ksuva
דאורייתא de'oraisa and מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה masneh al mah shekasuv
baTorah and therefore you don't succeed. And even though you don't succeed,
it's still ביאת זנות bi'as znus because the woman thinks that the
amount is actually less. All right, so that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
Now we continue. So both רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir say to directly try to change the amount doesn't achieve
anything.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says even the attempt makes it ביאת זנות.
bi'as znus. To be מוחל mochel the amount for רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda succeeds and is allowed, is permissible. For רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
presumably that's an interesting question. Can the woman not even be מוחל?
mochel? I mean, being מוחל mochel is it מתנה על מה שכתוב
בתורה? masneh al mah shekasuv baTorah? Being מוחל mochel is just being
מוחל, mochel, right? So it sounds like though from the גמרא Gemara
that even an attempt to be מוחל mochel wouldn't work for רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and it would also be ביאת זנות bi'as znus
just in the attempt. Now we're going to get a third position.
תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, רבי מאיר אומר כל
הפוחת לבתולה ממאתים ולאלמנה ממנה הרי זו ביאת זנות Rabbi Meir omer
kol hapoches liBsulah miMasayim uleAlmanah miManeh harei zu bi'as znus and in
any attempt to lower the amount is a ביאת זנות. bi'as znus.
רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose omer, now here's רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose,
we haven't seen this yet, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says רשאי, rishai,
you're allowed. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose actually says that you can
one step further than רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Not only can you
be מוחל mochel after you start with the base amount, but she
can actually from the outset stipulate to a lesser amount. And רבי
יהודה אומר, Rebbe Yehuda omer, the middle position: רצה כותב לבתולה שטר
של מאתים והיא כותבת לו התקבלתי ממך מנה.
ratza koteiv l'betulah shtar shel masayim v'hi koteves lo hiskabalti mimcha
maneh. You can start with two hundred and she can write a
receipt for a hundred, ולאלמנה מנה ul'almanah maneh or for a widow
a hundred, והיא כותבת לו התקבלתי ממך
חמשים v'hi koteves lo hiskabalti mimcha chamishim
and she can write a receipt for fifty. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: וסבר רבי יוסי רשאי? v'savar Rebbe Yossi rashai?
So now we have the third position of רבי יוסי, Rebbe Yossi,
right? רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says you can write a receipt but
you have to start with the base amount, רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
says you'll never succeed in lowering the amount and you'll just make
it into a בעילת זנות, beilat zenut, and רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi
says you can even start with a lesser amount. וסבר רבי יוסי
רשאי? v'savar Rebbe Yossi rashai? Does רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi say you're
allowed to start with a lesser amount? ורמינהו, v'raminhu, I'll ask you
on this: אין עושים כתובת אשה מטלטלין מפני תיקון העולם. ein osim
kesubas isha metaltelin mipnei tikkun ha'olam. We have a ברייתא braita that
says that you do not make the
כתובה kesubah of a woman, you don't designate chattel, right, not real
estate to be used to pay the כתובה kesubah of a woman.
Now again, as Michael has discussed and pointed out the other day,
this does not mean to take away her liens on the real
estate, that's something that we discussed, you're generally not able to do,
certainly not to make it less than the, to reduce it from
the right to have liens over two hundred זוז, zuz, but the
basic language of the כתובה kesubah is all of the property is
encumbered, כל נכסיי אחראין, kol nechasai achrayin, right? And that's a תנאי
בית דין. tenai beis din. So you're not here reducing the liens
on the real estate, but you're specifically designating chattel, מטלטלין, metaltelin, to
be used, the example I gave was your Wedgwood china, you're specifically
designating that to be used to pay off the כתובה, kesubah, not
to exclude from the liens on the real estate. Okay, so the
ברייתא braita says you don't do that, why? מפני תיקון העולם. mipnei
tikkun ha'olam. What's the תיקון העולם? tikkun ha'olam? The תיקון העולם tikkun
ha'olam is that the chattel will be destroyed, the Wedgwood china will
break, real estate can't get stolen, but china, who knows what can
happen to it? And therefore the woman will, or it'll reduce in
value, and then she'll be out
the full amount of the כתובה. kesubah. But we'll see, the question
is maybe you should just then go to the real estate? אין
עושים כתובת אשה מטלטלין מפני תיקון העולם. ein osim kesubas isha metaltelin
mipnei tikkun ha'olam. אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rebbe Yossi, רבי יוסי Rebbe
Yossi said, וכי מה תיקון העולם יש בזו? v'chi mah tikkun ha'olam
yesh b'zu? What type of like good societal function is
served by this? והלא אין קצובים, v'halo ein ketzuvim, the amount doesn't
remain fixed, ופוחתים, u'pochesim, and they could become worth less later on.
Now that's a little bizarre, that seems to be, no, he's talking
about chattel, so that seems to be exactly what the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma was saying, what's bothering you? So that's what the גמרא
Gemara is going to ask. גמרא Gemara says: תנא קמא נמי אין
עושים קאמר. Tanna Kamma nami ein osim ka'amar. It sounds like he
thought the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said you're allowed to make it,
and he was saying why should you be allowed to use chattel?
The chattel might go down in value, etc. But the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma also said you're not allowed to make it, so what
are they disagreeing about? So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא לאו הכי
קאמר, ela lav hachi ka'amar, this is what it must be saying:
במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, when are you not allowed to
make the chattel as the lien of the כתובה? kesubah? בשלא קיבל
עליו אחריות, bishelo kibel alav achrayus, when you don't accept responsibility for
its value, meaning that you only can collect from the chattel itself.
You're not allowed to designate the Wedgwood china and say this is
the only place you can collect the כתובה kesubah from, because then
what will happen? It'll break and the woman will be out. So
you're not allowed to do it if you don't accept responsibility for
it, you don't back it up with the liens on the real
estate. אבל קיבל עליו אחריות, aval kibel alav achrayus, if it was
backed up, you accepted responsibility that if it breaks then you will
be liable and you'll pay from the rest of your property, עושים,
osim, you are allowed to designate that she collect from chattel. ואתא
רבי יוסי למימר, v'asa Rebbe Yossi l'meimar, and רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi
comes along and says that's not enough. כי קיבל עליו אחריות אמאי
עושים? ki kibel alav achrayus amai osim? Why do you think you
solved the problem just because you accept liability for it, you the
husband? והלא אין קצובים, v'halo ein ketzuvim, the amount isn't fixed, ופוחתים,
u'pochesim, and it might go down in value. So even if you
accept liability for its breaking, but if it's still around, she's limited
to collect from the china, well the china might not be worth
as much when it comes time to collect her כתובה. kesubah. So
רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi says that's not good enough, you have not
fully protected the woman's interest. Okay, so that's a debate about designating
chattel, not real estate, and are you fully protecting the woman's interest?
So now let's see why the גמרא Gemara thinks that's relevant. So
the גמרא Gemara says like
this: השתא ומה התם, hashta u'mah hasam, over there, by the case
of the china, דדילמא פוחתי, d'dilma pochasi, maybe it'll go down in
value, חייש רבי יוסי, chayesh Rebbe Yossi, רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi is
concerned to protect her interests that it should never be worth less,
she should never collect less than the full amount. הכא דודאי קפחתה,
hacha d'vadai kapachta, here where you're clearly making the amount less, you're
stipulating that it should be a hundred, not two hundred, לא כל
שכן, lo kol shekein, how much more so should רבי יוסי Rebbe
Yossi not allow this? So why did רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi allow
you to stipulate less than two hundred if he's so interested in
protecting the woman's interest? The answer is
obvious, the answer is: הכי השתא, hachi hashta, what type of comparison
is that? התם לא ידעה דתמחול, hasam lo yada d'simchol, there
she's not aware that she should concede to it. She wants her
full two hundred and you the husband are saying Get it from
the צינא. tzeina. So she might be cheated out. She's demanding her
full 200 and you're setting up a scenario where she might not
be able to collect the full 200, the צינא tzeina might be
worth less later on. Okay, so that's one-sided. So you're not allowed
to do that one-sided to compromise her interests. אבל הכא, Aval hacha,
but in this case, ידעה וקמחלה, yad’ah v’kamachla, it was an agreement.
You wrote the כתובה Kesuvah initially for
100, so she would not have, so she was a party to
that. She agreed to that stipulation. So רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi allows
you a lesser amount if she agrees. He just says that if
she hasn't agreed, then he's obviously going to come and protect her
interests. Okay, so we have a three-way debate. רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi
says that if she agrees, you can have a lesser amount. רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says you can start, you must start with the
base amount, but then afterwards she can waive it and effectively make
it less. And רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says you can't even effectively
make it less, and even an attempt to do so is ביאת
זנות. be’as zenus. So now we're going to see how what the
implications of רבי מאיר’s Rebbi Meir’s position is and how do we
פסקן? pasken? Let's take a look.
אחותיה דרמי בר חמא, Achosei d’Rami Bar Chama, so the sister of
רמי בר חמא, Rami Bar Chama, הוי נסיבא לרבי אביא, havay nesiva
l’Rebbi Avya, was married to
רבי אביא. Rebbi Avya. אירכס כתובתה, Irkas kesuvashah, her כתובה Kesuvah was
lost. I’m not getting divorced; her כתובה Kesuvah was just lost. This
happens by the way more than once. I have gone back from
a wedding, sometimes I was the מסדר, mesader, sometimes I wasn’t, and
I get a call from the חתן chosson or we can't find
the כתובה, Kesuvah, what do we do? Okay, so first of all
you have to write a replacement כתובה, Kesuvah, and the replacement כתובה’s
Kesuvah’s called כתובה דאירכסא. Kesuvah d’irkesa. Okay, אירכס Irkas is the Aramaic
for lost, אירכס כתובתה. Irkas kesuvashah. And the language of that כתובה
Kesuvah is that the עדים eidim sign it, if you can get
the original עדים, eidim, and they say we originally signed a כתובה,
Kesuvah, דאירכס, d’irkas, and it was lost, and we're testifying that this
was what was in the original כתובה. Kesuvah.
Wait, do you write the whole thing all over again?
Pretty much. Okay, but you have to write, it's even a lengthier
text because you have to sort of indicate.
Are they allowed to live with each other until they have a
כתובה? Kesuvah?
Yeah, so I'm going to discuss that. Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. Okay, so the כתובה Kesuvah was lost, אירכס כתובתה. Irkas
kesuvashah. אתו לקמיה דרב יוסף, Aso l’kamei d’Rav Yosef, they came to
רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said to them:
הכי אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Hachi amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel,
this is רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name of שמואל,
Shmuel, זו דברי רבי מאיר. zu divrei Rebbi Meir. The idea that
it’s ביאת זנות be’as zenus is the position of רבי מאיר. Rebbi
Meir. אבל חכמים אומרים, Aval chachamim omrim, but the sages say: משהא
אדם עם אשתו שתים ושלש שנים בלא כתובה, mesha adam im ishto
shtayim v’shalosh shanim b’lo kesuvah, that you can go two or three
years without writing a substitute כתובה. Kesuvah. Now, what, just means, it
just means whatever, an indefinite period of time. I mean, probably not
like, not 10, 20, or 30 years, eventually you got to get
around to it, but there’s no big rush. Okay, that’s a way
of expressing that idea. Now, the first point is, whoever said that
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir said that you couldn’t hang around without a
written כתובה? Kesuvah? The amount, well, but the amount is still 100
or 200. You haven’t changed the amount, you just lost a piece
of paper. Remember we taught that even without the piece of paper
the obligations are there. But the גמרא Gemara reasonably understands, as Micah
was saying, that if just because the woman in her mind
thinks that the amount is less, even when it’s full, is enough
to create ביאת זנות, be’as zenus, so also the absence of the
piece of paper, of the document, is enough to create in her
mind a subjective ביאת זנות. be’as zenus. She feels if, this, my
husband can divorce me at any time and I'm not protected, I
don't have a document. Even if you say no, no, you have
the protection anyway, she doesn't feel protected, she doesn't have the document.
And maybe she knows that the debt is there, but she feels
he'll just claim he paid it. When I have a document, I
have proof that he hasn't paid. So the woman will reasonably feel
not protected, and therefore for רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir it would be
a ביאת זנות be’as zenus just to not have the physical document.
But the sages say that's not a problem. Okay, so now we're
going to have to see how we פסקן pasken because this is
an important issue. You're the rabbi, you get that call, do you
have to tell them don't do anything, I have to turn around
and get back to you and write you a כתובה Kesuvah or
fax you a כתובה Kesuvah for you to sign, what do you
have to do? How do we פסקן? pasken? Like רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir or like the חכמים? Chachamim? So let's take a look. אמר
ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said back: ולאמר רב
נחמן אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי מאיר בגזירותיו? V’la’amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel
halacha k’Rebbi Meir bigzeirosov? But one minute, it might be true that
the sages argue on רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, but we also say
we rule like רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir with his edicts, his גזירות.
gzeiros. אי הכי, Ei hachi, okay fine, if you rule like רבי
מאיר, Rebbi Meir, if that's the way you feel, זיל כתוב לה,
zil kesov lah, go write her a substitute כתובה. Kesuvah. So it
sounds like we פסקן pasken like רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir in this
case. Now, it is funny that the גמרא Gemara calls this a
גזירה. gzeira. Right? גזירות Gzeiros are normally like safeguards, not necessarily a
safeguard that you might do a rabbinic transgression, you might be safeguarding
other types of things, but the גמרא Gemara often distinguishes between גזירותיו
gzeirosov and תקנותיו. takanosov. But this is somehow seen as a גזירה
gzeira in the sense of protecting the sanctity of marriage or the
proper sense of the context of what marriage is with all of
its protection. So it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara calls this idea
of labeling it ביאת זנות be’as zenus as a type of a
גזירה. gzeira. Okay, not a גזירה gzeira again like don't read by
candlelight on שבת, Shabbos, you might tip the candle, but a גזירה
gzeira to protect the institute and the protections of marriage. Okay, so
this sounds like we rule like רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. כי אתא
רב דימי, Ki asa Rav Dimi, so we'll see to the end
and then I'll tell you what we do למעשה. l’ma’aseh. כי
אתא רב דימי, Ki ata Rav Dimi, when רב דימי Rav Dimi
came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר שמואל בן פזי amar Shmuel
ben Pazi אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
משום בר קפרא. mishum Bar Kappara. Now actually we're about to get
into a little complicated piece, so let me just pause here and
tell you what we do הלכה למעשה. halacha l'maaseh. So הלכה למעשה
halacha l'maaseh we do very quickly try to create a substitute כתובה.
ketubah.
By the way, it's not just people that call you from the
wedding and they misplaced it. More than once I've had a call
from a couple that's been married twenty-thirty years and they can't locate
their כתובה. ketubah. They move, they can't locate their כתובה. ketubah. Or
my parents actually were once looking at the כתובה ketubah that they
had hung up on the wall and realized that the, no, not
a mistake, but that the signatures had completely whatever, dissolved, whatever, disappeared,
faded, so they were illegible. So you have to write a substitute
כתובה. ketubah. But can you say, do you say that you have
to stop living together, sleep in separate
rooms until you do it? So in principle that's the answer, but
the רמ"א Rama actually says that nowadays, after תקנת רבנו גרשום, takanat
Rabbeinu Gershom, that a man cannot divorce his wife, a husband cannot
divorce his wife against her will, so you don't, it's not the
problem of ביאת זנות. bi'at znut. The problem of ביאת זנות bi'at
znut is she feels that even as they're having sex, it's not
really in, with the sort of protections of marriage because maybe he's
just using me and he's going to divorce me tomorrow
morning. And she has to feel protected. So the כתובה ketubah protects
her against easy divorce. So the basic idea of the protection is
she knows he's not just going to callously divorce her. So the
רמ"א Rama says, it's interesting that he focuses it on that way,
that now that a woman can't be divorced against her will, even
without the written כתובה, ketubah, she knows that she's protected in that
way, so it's not a ביאת זנות. bi'at znut. Nevertheless, we try
to take care of it as soon as possible, but we don't
tell them stop living together until I get taken care of.
Is that for ספרדים Sefardim also?
So that's a good question. I don't know. But I mean most
ספרדים Sefardim nowadays have one way or another adopted רבנו גרשום, Rabbeinu
Gershom, but it's an interesting question about how ספרדים Sefardim deal with
that. I don't know the full answer to that.
And you said you have to write a new one if even
some signatures
are, you can't use the same one even if the signatures are
faded?
Yeah, דווקא davka you have to write a new one because,
no, because you have to write, no, no, because it's not giving
honest, well, no, because the need is to testify. There's a whole
problem about writing two כתובות, ketubos, because maybe
you,
even if you have the same witnesses, why not just rewrite it?
Why do you have to make it, why do you have to
use a different נוסח nusach if you have the same witnesses? If
you had different witnesses, you'd understand why, because other witnesses didn't witness
the original event. But if it's the same witnesses, the reason you
can't is because maybe the woman is just saying that she lost
the כתובה ketubah and now she's going to have two כתובות ketubos
and she's going to use it to collect twice. All right, how
do you know though? Maybe she managed to create a facsimile. The
whole problem, anyway, you don't write the identical one because then you're
afraid that there are two documents, equivalent documents on the same debt.
But isn't that exactly what you're protecting against by having the different
נוסח? nusach? Because if she has, if she has the original,
because a different נוסח nusach says that the original one was lost,
so therefore, but
if
she has the two different courts or something. That's true. I guess
if it's that way, once he pays he's handed over the first
כתובה, ketubah, then it doesn't matter whether it's the same נוסח nusach
or different נוסח. nusach.
Unless he also gets a receipt, that's what they say. That's true.
I'm not sure. I'm not sure. I'd have to figure that out.
All right, all right, all right, I hear the question. Let's go
on. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, כי אתא
רב דימי.
Ki ata
Rav Dimi. Now we're going to have a question about what was
the scope of this debate of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi who says
that you can lower and the others who say you cannot lower
the amount, at least initially.
כי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי שמעון בן פזי אמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי משום בר קפרא,
Ki ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi mishum Bar Kappara, said the
following: מחלוקת בתחילה. Machloket betchila.
The debate of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi that says that you can
change the amount and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda say you can't, at least initially,
is only at the beginning of the wedding. אבל בסוף, Aval besof,
at the end, דברי הכל אינה מוחלת. divrei hakol eina mochelet. Even
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says you can't change the amount. Now the
question's going to be what the end means, but for now let's
just say after they've had sex, so then the obligations kick in.
So then רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would say you can't change the
amount. I mean he could be מוחל, mochel, but to change the
base amount, the initial base amount, you have to do it before
the obligation begins, right? Once the obligation begins, then he's obligated. Then
she could be מוחלת, mochelet, but the obligation has been defined once
they
actually have had sex. Okay, so אינה מוחלת. eina mochelet. ורבי יוחנן
אמר, v'Rabbi Yochanan amar, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, בין בזו
ובין בזו מחלוקת. bein b'zo u'vein b'zo machloket. No, they debate both
cases. אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abbahu, now we're going to try
to clarify what beginning and end means. לדידי מיפרשו לי מיניה דרבי
יוחנן, Lididi mifarshu li minei d'Rabbi Yochanan, it was explained to me
the position of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in the name of רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, excuse me, דאנא ורבי יהושע בן לוי, d'ana v'Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi, I and רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi, the first opinion, לא פליגינן, lo plaginnun, we don't debate. מה
בתחילה דקאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Ma betchila d'ka amar Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi, what beginning did רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi say... That the debate is at the outset, that means תחלת
t'chilas חופה, chuppah, at the, that means the beginning of the חופה,
chuppah, that they don't debate that before the חופה, chuppah, I'm sorry,
that that's when they debate before the before the חופה. chuppah. ומאי
U-mai סוף, sof, and at the end when everybody agrees you can't
change it is סוף sof ביאה, biah, is when they've actually had
sex. וכי Ve-chi קאמינא ka amina אנא ana בין bein בזו be-zu
ובין u-vein בזו be-zu מחלוקת, machlokes, and when I say that they
debate both cases, beginning and end, I mean a different beginning and
end. I mean תחלת t'chilas חופה, chuppah, the beginning of the חופה,
chuppah, before the חופה, chuppah, וסוף ve-sof חופה, chuppah, or after the
חופה chuppah but before sex, והיא ve-hi תחלת t'chilas ביאה, biah, okay,
which is the beginning of sex. So basically, this is going to
get confusing, okay, but basically we're identifying three places, okay? There's
חופה, chuppah,
there's ביאה, biah, okay, and there's ביאה, biah, right? And now this
partly goes to the whole question, right, about when do the כתובה
kesubah obligations begin? If you remember the other day we had the
question like when the תוספת tosefes begins. Does the תוספת tosefes begin
at חופה? chuppah? Does the תוספת tosefes begin at ביאה? biah? So
in a related way the question is when has the obligations begun
that it's too late to change the amounts? Because once the obligation
began you can always be מוחל mochel but to fundamentally change the
amount. Okay? So the first position of רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rebbe
Yehoshua ben Levi, right? רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rebbe Yehoshua ben Levi,
this is the way the גמרא Gemara is going to sort of
say it, says they argue at תחילה, t'chilah, okay? So תחילה t'chilah
here, this is what's going to be called before, is going to
be called תחלת t'chilas חופה, chuppah, yeah, right, this really means before.
Okay? So רבי יהושע בן לוי Rebbe Yehoshua ben Levi is going
to say,
רבי יהושע
בן
לוי, Rebbe Yehoshua ben Levi, okay, and this is רבי יוחנן. Rebbe
Yochanan. The reason I'm making a whole chart is because we're going
to have more than one version of this. Okay? So רבי יהושע
בן לוי Rebbe Yehoshua ben Levi says here is מחלוקת. machlokes. They
argue at תחילה. t'chilah. And here, everybody agrees,
everybody says can't change. Everybody says
cannot change, right?
Cannot change. Okay? That's what he says. רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan says
they argue in both cases, but what he, but what, now the
way it's being explained, they argue in both cases תחילה t'chilah and
סוף, sof, means תחלת t'chilas חופה chuppah before the חופה chuppah and
סוף sof חופה chuppah means at the חופה. chuppah. And therefore really
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rebbe Yehoshua ben Levi and רבי יוחנן Rebbe
Yochanan really agree that the מחלוקת machlokes is through the חופה, chuppah,
can you change the amount? And everybody agrees when you get to
the ביאה biah you can't change the amount. Okay? So that's that
version.
We don't know what רבי יהושע בן לוי Rebbe Yehoshua ben Levi
would say about חופה chuppah though, right?
No, we're saying that they all agree.
He didn't say it.
He didn't say it. We're making them all agree. Okay, so גמרא
Gemara says like this. כי Ki
אתא ata רבין Ravin אמר, amar, now when רבין Ravin came he
had a different version of the positions of this debate. He said
כי ki אתא ata רבין Ravin אמר amar רבי Rebbe שמעון Shimon
בן ben פזי Pazi אמר amar רבי יהושע בן לוי Rebbe Yehoshua
ben Levi משום mishum בר bar קפרא, Kappara, that the רבי יהושע
בן לוי Rebbe Yehoshua ben Levi position was the following.
מחלוקת Machlokes לבסוף. le-vasof. They argue at the end. אבל Aval בתחילה
bit'chilah at the outset דברי divrei הכל ha-kol מוכלת, mocheles, even everybody,
even רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says you can change the amount if
you do it at the beginning. Okay? ורבי יוחנן אמר Ve-Rebbe Yochanan
amar בין bein בזו be-zu ובין u-vein בזו be-zu מחלוקת. machlokes. No,
they argue beginning and end. So this is like the mirror image.
They argue at the end, they agree at the beginning that it's
possible. And now we're going to make the two say the same
thing. אמר Amar רבי אבהו Rebbe Abahu לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דרבי
יוחנן, l'didi m'farsha li minei d'Rabbi Yochanan it was explained to me
in the name of רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan דאנא ורבי יהושע בן
לוי לא פליגינן אהדדי, d'ana v'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi lo palginan adadi,
we don't argue with one another. מאי Mai לבסוף le-vasof דאמר de-amar
רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rebbe Yehoshua ben Levi, when רבי יהושע בן
לוי Rebbe Yehoshua ben Levi
says that at the end, that's where they debate, that means סוף
sof חופה. chuppah. The end of the חופה, chuppah, meaning after the
חופה chuppah before the sex. ומאי U-mai תחילה, t'chilah, where's the תחילה
t'chilah that everybody says okay? תחלת T'chilas חופה, chuppah, the beginning of
the חופה, chuppah, before the חופה. chuppah. וכי Ve-chi קאמינא ka amina
אנא, ana, and when I, רבי יוחנן, Rebbe Yochanan, say I'm going
to put it on the board בין bein בזו be-zu ובין u-vein
בזו be-zu מחלוקת, machlokes, they debate both cases, תחלת t'chilas ביאה biah
וסוף ve-sof ביאה, biah, meaning it's the beginning of the ביאה, biah,
meaning the חופה chuppah after the חופה chuppah and the after the
sex. So basically this version
has them say the mirror image. Okay, I need another color. What
happened? I had a whole bunch of them. I had all of
them but I put them away.
Break it open, the new pack.
Okay, so
your first version was Lou's version? The one on the board?
I don't know, Ravin or something. Okay, so this says they argue
at the beginning, not at the end. The other version says
that at the beginning everybody says,
everybody says can change,
okay, and at the end,
and the end is the מחלוקת, machlokes, okay, and רבי יוחנן Rebbe
Yochanan in this version says בין בזו בין בזו מחלוקת
bein b'zu bein
b'zu machlokes means means these two, so they're not really arguing. Okay,
according to this, you see how we managed to make a third
case so we shift it so that they can agree. So according
to this, everybody agrees before the חופה chuppah it can change, and
everybody disagrees
after the, after the חופה, chuppah, after the ביאה. biah. And that's
how we made them the same. According to the first version, the
green version, it's the opposite. Everybody agrees after the ביאה biah it
can't change and the מחלוקת machlokes is in all the stages before
the ביאה. biah. Okay, so two different versions of it, but in
both cases having רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהושע בן לוי
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi say the same thing. Now the גמרא Gemara
ends this thing and the following: אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa,
says רב פפא, Rav Pappa, אי לאו דאמר רבי אבהו i lav
d'amar Rabbi Abbahu לדידי le-didi מפרשא miforsha לי li מיניה minei דרבי
יוחנן de-Rebbe Yochanan, דאנא de-ana ורבי יהושע בן לוי u-Rebbe Yehoshua ben
Levi לא lo פליגינן peliginan אהדדי, a-hadadi, if we had not had
this statement of רב פפא Rav Pappa in the name of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to say that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי
יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi were really saying the same
thing, so הוינא אמינא havina amina רבי יוחנן ורבי יהושע בן לוי
פליגי, Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi pligi, I would have said
no, I would have said רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהושע
בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi are disagreeing, are really disagreeing as
to the debates of the תנאים Tannaim here, they're not saying the
same things, but רב דימי ורבין
לא פליגי, Rav Dimi v'Ravin lo pligi, but the two versions of
the רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan debate, those
don't really argue.
Why? מאי סוף דקאמר רבין סוף חופה mai sof d'ka'amar Ravin sof
chuppah and מאי תחלה דקאמר רב דימי תחלת ביאה. mai techilah d'ka'amar
Rav Dimi techilas biah. Okay, now and I'm questioning if I want
to try to make this work out, but what I would have
said is rather than this which has basically רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
and רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
agreeing, it's the same thing in different ways, but the מחלוקת machlokes
is what רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said and what רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan said, the green version or the red version. There's another way
to do it, I don't think it's worth doing it on the
board but you'll trust me, there's another way to do it that
takes רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi at face value and has them actually arguing but has
the two versions of רב דימי Rav Dimi and רבין Ravin to
effectively mean the same thing, just using different languages for saying the
same thing. Okay, and he says I would have rather, if we're
going to reduce the debate, I would have rather reduced the debate
between רבין Ravin and רב דימי Rav Dimi rather than have collapsed
the debate of רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi and
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So the גמרא Gemara says why, what difference
does it make once we're trying to collapse one of the debates?
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי קא משמע לן, mai ka mashma
lan, what are you teaching me? הא קא משמע לן דפליגי תרי
אמוראי טעמא דנפשייהו ולא פליגי
תרי אמוראי אליבא דחד אמורא. Ha ka mashma lan d'pligi trei amorai
ta'ama d'nafshaihu v'lo pligi trei amorai aliba d'chad amora. It would be
better to say that the two אמוראים Amoraim are disagreeing based on
logic than that they're disagreeing on what an אמורא Amora said. Meaning,
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi and רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, if they're really arguing, if they're not saying the same thing,
what they're arguing is what area does it make sense to say
the מחלוקת machlokes occurred between רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי, Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbi
Yosi, right? So they're arguing about a סברא. sevara. So it's better
to say that they're arguing about a סברא sevara and they're arguing
against one another than to say that there's a debate about what
רבי יוחנן ורבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
actually said. What difference does it make? Because as רש"י Rashi says
and תוספות Tosafos says more succinctly, he says we always argue for
סברא. sevara. That's what the whole ש"ס Shas is: I think this
way, you think that way. So רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi thinks that the debate makes more sense in this realm
and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan thinks the debate makes more sense in
that realm. That's fine. But to say that there's a debate about
what they originally said means that there's actually a problem in transmission,
right? That there's a different version that רבין Ravin had one version
of what they said
and רב דימי Rav Dimi had a different version. So that actually
means that somebody got it wrong, got the transmission wrong. So he
says I would have rather said that they're arguing and they're arguing
in the סברא sevara of where, you know, it makes sense that
the מחלוקת machlokes occurs and said that there rather than saying that
there was a debate about the right version of what the two
of them said. We do have that but if I had to
choose, I'd rather it be a debate in סברא. sevara. Fine. All
right, that's the end of that, let's not belabor that point anymore.
Next משנה. mishna. And now we're having, okay, going to see if
we can catch up. נותנים לבתולה שנים עשר חודש משתבעה הבעל לפרנס
את עצמה. notnim l'besulah shneim asar chodesh mishetva'ah haba'al l'farnes es atzmah.
So from the time that the husband says, right, everybody thinks that
oh twelve months after קידושין kiddushin they got married. No. Twelve months
after קידושין, kiddushin, then she might have got married at the age
of two or the age, the old age of
five, okay, it was only many years later the husband said now
it's time for us to start living together. Okay, so from the
moment that he says I think we have to move from קידושין
kiddushin to נשואין, nissuin,
from that point on she's got twelve months to get her what
do you call it trousseau together and to say fine, I'm ready
to get married but you got to give me twelve months. Okay,
so she's got twelve months to take care of getting ready. Presumably
that assumes that he'd like to get married tomorrow but she's entitled
to twelve months from the time he... Okay, so they're already קידושין
kiddushin and now he's saying I want to move on to נישואין
nissuin and we give her 12 months to get her stuff together.
וכשם שנותנין לאישה כך נותנין לאיש. U'keshem shenotnin l'isha kach notnin l'ish.
But similarly, you know, he can say I want to take 12
months to get, to get the house ready and to get the,
you know, and to get everything prepared for us to get married.
Of course the question is then why was he the one, then
why was he the one saying let's get married? Maybe she was
the one saying, it's a little hard to understand the scenario because
it seems like just the implicit social contract here is that he's
the one that gets just to say when it's time. But anyway,
maybe the bride's father is pushing him or something. And whatever the
scenario is, he's entitled to 12 months as well if he needs
it. לפרנס את עצמו. L'farnes et atzmo. ואלמנה שלושים יום. V'almana shloshim
yom. That's a first marriage. But if however it's a second marriage,
so then it's assumed that she's more independent and therefore she's more,
she doesn't need as much time, you know, to, to get her
trousseau together. And maybe also they wouldn't make as much of a
bigger deal of it. הגיע זמן ולא נישאו. Higia zman v'lo nisu.
Now the 12 months are up and they're not yet married. And
remember this was brought in in the very first דף daf of
the מסכת. masechet. There's the whole question of who's to blame. The
משנה mishna doesn't discuss who's to blame, but it just says the
following: they're not married, אוכלת משלו. ochelet mishelo. Then he has to
start now paying the food bills, right? Once there's נישואין, nissuin, he
has a חיוב chiyuv of מזונות. mezonot. He has a חיוב chiyuv
to support her. So if they should be married by now and
they're not, and the beginning of the מסכת masechet discussed does it
matter who's to blame or not, but now he starts, she starts
now, you know, she eats from his, on his account. He basically
has to pay for her food starting now, for her expenses. אוכלת
משלו. ochelet mishelo. ואוכלת בתרומה. V'ochelet b'teruma. If he's a כהן, kohen,
he can feed her תרומה. teruma. Okay, because תרומה teruma is cheaper.
Okay, which basically shows that a woman, a wife of a כהן
kohen is entitled to eat from תרומה teruma even before the נישואין,
nissuin, even at the אירוסין. erusin. So it's telling you two things.
Number one, from laws of תרומה, teruma, even though she's not yet
נשואה, nesua, she's only ארוסה arusa to a כהן, kohen, she's allowed
to eat it. And number two, in terms of his obligation to
feed her, he can satisfy that by feeding her תרומה, teruma, by
giving her
תרומה. teruma. ורבי טרפון אומר נותנין לה הכל תרומה. V'Rabbi Tarfon omer
notnin la hakol teruma. He can give the whole amount in תרומה.
teruma. רבי עקיבא אומר מחצה חולין ומחצה תרומה. Rabbi Akiva omer mechtza
chullin u'mechtza teruma. Now half has to be חולין. chullin. Why? Because
half of the month, not really half but only once you get
חומרא דרבי זירא, chumra d'Rabbi Zeira, but anyway a good part of
the month she's טמאה, tme'ah, she's a נידה. niddah. And when she's
a נידה niddah she can't eat תרומה. teruma. So it's not fair
to give her תרומה teruma that she'll have to sell and then
get in exchange less חולין. chullin. He has to provide her at
least half of the amount חולין, chullin, stuff that she can eat
even when she's טמאה. tme'ah. היבם... Hayabam... what? Let me back before
for a second.
The הגיע זמן ולא נישאו...
higia
zman v'lo nisu...
about the אלמנה שלושים יום, almana shloshim yom, so she gets 30
days. Does he also have
a 30-day time frame?
Presumably. Presumably. היבם אינו מאכיל בתרומה. Hayabam eino ma'achil b'teruma. Let's say
a כהן kohen was married to a woman, כהן kohen died, and
now his brother the כהן kohen has to do יבום. yibbum. He
hasn't done יבום yibbum yet, she's waiting for יבום yibbum to be
done, she's שומרת יבם. shomeret yabam. So in that case she cannot
eat תרומה. teruma. Okay, even if and we don't like say there's
like a 12-month clock and afterwards she's able to eat תרומה. teruma.
So even though it's somewhat analogous, she's waiting to get married to
this יבם, yabam, nevertheless there's no תביעה להינשא tviyah l'hinnasei situation, you
might think it's even more, there's a מצווה mitzvah to do it,
but no, she's not yet, she's not entitled to eat תרומה. teruma.
עשתה שישה חודשים בפני הבעל ושישה חודשים בפני היבם. Asta shisha chodashim
bifnei habaal v'shisha chodashim bifnei hayabam. Let's say the husband, the כהן
kohen husband was אירוסין... erusin... was מאורס me'oras and he said let's
get married and it was six months and then he dropped dead.
And now it's six months that she's waiting for יבום. yibbum. ואפילו
כולן בפני הבעל, Va'afilu kulan bifnei habaal, or it was one day
before the נישואין nissuin and her, the כהן kohen she was מקודשת
mekudeshet to, one day before the נישואין nissuin after the 11 months
and 29 days dropped dead on her. חסר יום אחד בפני היבם,
Chasar yom echad bifnei hayabam, and then that last day was obviously
waiting, you know, waiting for the guy to do יבום. yibbum. או
כולן בפני היבם חסר יום אחד בפני הבעל. O kulan bifnei hayabam
chasar yom echad bifnei habaal. That's obviously... this is pretty self-apparent. Or
she waited one day, you know, after the קידושין kiddushin to this
guy and he dropped dead and now it's 11 months and 29
days in front of the יבם. yabam. In all those cases אינה
אוכלת בתרומה. eina ochelet b'teruma. She does not eat תרומה. teruma. Now
רש"י Rashi says that that last case is obvious because the משנה
mishna made it sound like she could wait five years for יבום
yibbum and not eat תרומה. teruma. Okay, we'll get, and in tomorrow's
דף daf I'll discuss what תוספות's Tosafot position on this is. רש"י
Rashi said that last case was a little bit of a throw-in
because even if you wait five years before the יבם, yabam, she
doesn't eat תרומה. teruma. She only eats תרומה teruma in a, in
the case of a normal נישואין, nissuin, not in the case of
a waiting יבום. yibbum. All right?
And she needs...
Right, when she does get married, she will for sure.
ובת כהן אם אין לה זרע היא יכולה לחזור לבית אביה. U'bat
kohen im ein la zera hi yechola lachzor l'veit aviha.
Exactly. זו משנה ראשונה. Zu mishna rishona. That was the first teaching.
בית דין של אחריהן אמרו. Beit din shel achareihen amru. Now by
the way משנה ראשונה... mishna rishona... does literally mean משנה mishna as
a text. There is, I mean, there's a whole literature about משנה
ראשונה. mishna rishona. Basically, there was early collections of משניות mishnayos and
even when rulings changed later, those early collections were not rejected. So
this preserves this original text of the original משנה. mishna. Again, the
text doesn't mean a written text, it was oral, but the original
text of the original משנה mishna was this. And here, now, but
here's an update. Okay, after that, it was revised in the following
way. And it's interesting that we don't just discard that original text.
Why quote it? Why not just tell me the הלכה? halacha? A
phrase הגמרא haGemara has is משנה ראשונה לא זזה ממקומה, mishna rishona
lo zazah mimkomah, which is basically we preserve our earlier texts. Okay,
so that was the way it was. Here, however, is the update.
The update is, בית דין של אחריהן אמרו, beis din shel achareihen
amru, אין האשה אוכלת בתרומה עד שתיכנס לחופה. ein ha'ishah ocheles b'serumah
ad she'tikaneis l'chupah. No, that
as we'll see, for various reasons, we don't want a woman—while his
obligation to feed her begins after twelve months, we don't want her
to start eating תרומה terumah until חופה, chupah, which by the way
is to her benefit, which means that he has to pay a
higher food bill. He has to feed her all חולין, chullin, he
can't feed her תרומה.
terumah. So we don't want her giving—
Right, that's going to be the reason. Let's take a look at
הגמרא. haGemara.
Just this example that she's a בת כהן, bas kohen, she still—the
future husband, יבם, yavam, can't—cannot give her תרומה terumah even though she
eats it at home?
That's a good point. We'll see about that. I think—I think that's
going to come up. Okay, so I'm going to hold off on
that, answering that. That's a good question. מנא הני מילי? mina hani
mili? Where is this from? That a woman has twelve months from,
you know, to say, to not be rushed into נישואין. nisuin. So
אמר רב חסדא אמר קרא, amar Rav Chisda amar kra, the verse
says, ויאמר אחיה ואמה תשב הנערה אתנו ימים או עשור. vayomer achiha
v'immah teshev hana'arah ittanu yamim o asor.
So this is by, right, רבקה, Rivka, her mother and brother said,
let her stay with us for days or ten. מאי ימים? mai
yamim? What do days mean? אילימא תרי יומי? ilima trei yomei? If
it's two days, משתעי אינש הכי? mishtai inash hachi? Do people say—is
talk this way? אמרו ליה תרי יומי? amru leh trei yomei? Give
us two days. אמרו להו לא. amru lehu lo. אמרו ליה, amru
leh, so then they'll say to them, okay, אלא עשרה יומי, ella
asarah yomei, give us ten days? Give us two days or ten
days, right? You normally—you don't bargain up, you tend to bargain down.
So אלא מאי ימים שנה? ella mai yamim shanah? When it says
give us a day, it means give us a year. And if
not a year, give us ten months.
Okay. דכתיב ימים תהיה גאולתו. d'chsiv yamim tihyeh ge'ulaso. In a full
year can—you can redeem by the house of—by the case of selling
the house in a—in a walled city. ואימא חודש? v'eima chodesh? Maybe
ימים yamim means a month? And maybe it means a month or
ten days, not a year or ten months? דכתיב עד חודש ימים,
d'chsiv ad chodesh yamim, a month of days. So אמרי דנין ימים
סתם מימים סתם. amri danin yamim stam miyamim stam. Take ימים yamim
when it comes unqualified from where it says ימים yamim unqualified. ואין
דנין ימים סתם מימים שנאמר בהן חודש. v'ein danin yamim stam miyamim
shene'emar bahen chodesh. And you don't learn from a case where it
says חודש ימים chodesh yamim where חודש chodesh qualifies it. But ימים
yamim by itself would mean a year. So you see that they
had a right to ask for a year. And then the עבד
eved just says, don't hold me back. So he pressured them, but
at least in principle we get an idea that they have the
right to hold back for a year. Okay, so now הגמרא haGemara
says like this. Now, אמר רבי זירא, amar Rabbi Zeira, תנא, tana,
we תנא tana a ברייתא. braisa. קטנה בין היא ובין אביה יכולין
לעכב. ketannah bein hi u'vein aviha yecholin l'akev. While she's still a
קטנה, ketannah, either she or the father can say, I don't want
to get married, I'm still a קטנה, ketannah, okay, so it's too
soon. As long—as long as she's a קטנה. ketannah. Okay, so this
is a new idea, that the whole idea of a year is
when she's no longer a קטנה, ketannah, but once she's a
קטנה—or ketannah when she agreed.
Well, right, but the idea that it's a year—as long as she's
a קטנה ketannah she can basically hold back.
Now, by the—okay, by the way, the question here is, what do
you mean
יכולין לעכב? yecholin l'akev? Why, are you going to take a woman
kicking and screaming—screaming into the—the חופה? chupah? Like let's say, you know,
let's say—let's say it's like more than a year. You say, okay,
you're only allowed to postpone a year. Let's say she postpones more
than a year. So what are you going to do to her?
You know? What does that mean? So it could mean that more
than a year, he doesn't have to—if you go more than the
allowed amount, he doesn't have to start feeding. But fine, but what's
a נפקא מינה? nafka mina? Tell me I've got five years, he
doesn't have to feed me during the five years. Tell me I've
got one year and I refuse, he also doesn't feed me during
the period where I'm refusing to go to the חופה. chupah. What
difference does it make? Do you understand the question I'm asking?
What difference
does it make to say she has a right to postpone? She
has a right to wait. Let's say she didn't have a right
to wait. What are you going to say? You're not going to
force her into the חופה chupah against her will. What are you
going to do to her if you say you don't have a
right to wait? I don't have a right to wait and I'm
still refusing to go.
Yeah, but if she's a—if she's his slave, he can also marry
her, can't he marry—
No, well, but—but now we're going to say that—but it's not talking—by
קטנה ketannah we'd be talking about a נערה. na'arah. Anyway, the point
תוספות Tosafos says to be is that if you would say she
didn't have a right, then it's sort of anticipating what we're going
to get to in the later, sort of, you know, גמרות, gemaros,
which is about when a woman isn't living up to her marital
obligations, that you start like reducing the amount of her כתובה. kesuvah.
You start fining her, you know, and, you know, in order—in order
to get compliance. So, but the assumption is that if you didn't
say she has a right for a year, or let's say—actually it's—the
year's up and... But he still refuses, there might be some financial
penalties that we actually impose in order to get compliance. Okay, we
might lower the amount of the כתובה. Ketubah. But it is interesting
wondering what does this mean you have the right to do it?
What would be the alternative? All right? So now the גמרא Gemara
is saying that as long as she's a קטנה, Ketana, even more
than a year, she and her father have a right to postpone.
So meaning they agreed to get married and now
they agreed to get married when she was three, and the guy
when she was seven said okay let's actually—they had קידושין Kiddushin at
three. At seven, the guy said let's start living together, and she
and the father had a radical idea and said you know it
might be better to wait till she's בת מצוה. Bat Mitzvah. Okay,
they're entitled to push it off that much. Okay?
בין היא ובין אביה יכולים
לעכב.
Bein hi uvein aviha yecholim
le'akev. So גמרא Gemara says בשלמא אי איהי מעכבא Bishlama ei ihi
me'akva that she can postpone it, we understand because, you know, that's
a חידוש. Chidush. אלא אביה, Ela aviha, but by the father, אי
ניחא לה, ei nicha lah, if she wants to do נישואין Nissu'in
and there's already been קידושין, Kiddushin, אביה מאי נפקא ליה מינה? aviha
mai nafka lei mina? Right? What's the father's right to postpone it?
Meaning if she says I'm not ready yet for marriage and I'm
a קטנה, Ketana, we understand that that's a legitimate claim. But if
the father says I'm not ready to have her yet married, why
should that be a legitimate claim? So the גמרא Gemara says what
are you talking about? The
father—well, let's take a look. But exactly what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say. It's actually interesting, גמרא Gemara could have said because
as long as there's no נישואין, Nissu'in, he's entitled to her מעשי
ידיה ma'aseh yadeha and all those other things. But let's see what
the גמרא Gemara does say. סבר, Sevar, because the father feels, השתא
לא ידעה, hashta lo yade'ah, she doesn't know, she's seven years old,
she thinks she's ready, so he thinks she's okay. למחר מימרדא, lemachar
mimreda, you know, after she gets married she'll be too young and
then she'll say she doesn't want to stay with this guy, and
תימאס temayes and you know reject him, ונפקא venafka and then he'll
divorce her because—ואתיא ונפלה עילואי, ve'asya venafala ilavai, and then she's going
to be my responsibility. Okay? Now this is a—I gotta tell you—a
funny גמרא, Gemara, because it's more obvious the reason he could say
I don't want to have her, you know, go ahead in נישואין
Nissu'in is because as long as she remains at home, I'm entitled
to her like מעשי ידיה, ma'aseh yadeha, right? Before נישואין. Nissu'in. But
maybe the גמרא Gemara said that's not legitimate. The guy did קידושין,
Kiddushin, he's ready to get married, why do you have a right
to stand in the way? So it needed to find a reason
within the marriage itself that he had a legitimate claim. And yeah,
he's not in loco parentis, he is parentis, you know. So he
says I actually think this is a bad idea and you should
trust my judgment at this stage. But the other interesting thing is
that after נישואין, Nissu'in, technically she won't be his responsibility. If she's
divorced after נישואין, Nissu'in, she's not his responsibility. So even saying, but
I guess again from the social realities I'll be expected to deal
with her and it's just going to be—it's going to be difficult.
So either she or the father while she's still a קטנה Ketana
can say it's not yet the right time. Okay.
אמר רבי אבא בר לוי, Amar Rabbi Abba bar Levi, אין פוסקין
על הקטנה להשיאה כשהיא קטנה. ein poskin al haketana lehasi'ah keshehi ketana.
You do not make a deal with the husband for a, you
know, for a קטנה Ketana to marry her off while she's still
a קטנה. Ketana. Okay? We just saw that—but this is not doing
קידושין, Kiddushin, this is about to marry her off, the נישואין Nissu'in
which we just said, you know, that she or the father can
be מעכב. me'akev. So once you say she or the father can
be מעכב, me'akev, the גמרא Gemara is pretty much signaling that the
גמרא Gemara doesn't think it's a good idea for a woman to
do נישואין Nissu'in while she's a קטנה. Ketana. By the way, this
is worth noting. I don't know how much better this makes it,
but you know people are rightly scandalized when you talk about קידושי
קטנה. Kiddushei ketana. Here he is, she's what, she's five years old
and she's married to this guy? So קידושין Kiddushin is only like
on paper, you know, I mean it's not—they haven't really started living
together in a sexual—having a life—sexual life. That begins at נישואין. Nissu'in.
And this גמרא Gemara is basically saying we don't want that to
happen while she's a קטנה. Ketana. So okay, once she's בת מצוה,
Bat Mitzvah, fine. I mean, again, not that that's so much better,
but at least then at least she's mature. I mean there are,
you know, people—girls do have whatever, you know, it does happen, girls
have sex by, you know, the age of 12 and 13 and
so on, not that it's a good thing. Okay? But at least
the גמרא Gemara is saying here we don't want the נישואין Nissu'in
to take place. So first it starts by saying she or the
father can—can stop it, which is obviously indicating that the גמרא Gemara
thinks it's a good idea to stop it at that—you know, to
not have it happen. Then the גמרא Gemara goes one step further
and is black and white and says you should not do this,
not just you have the right to stop it but you should
not marry your daughter off, do the נישואין Nissu'in while she is
a קטנה. Ketana. Okay.
But
the father sells the
daughter as a
slave... קטנה... Ketana... Yeah, sold as a slave.
Or marries her as a
קטנה.
Ketana. Which one?
He can marry her as a קטנה Ketana but that's קידושין Kiddushin
but she doesn't start living with the guy yet. That's נישואין. Nissu'in.
And so if he did so it would be after—נישואין Nissu'in would
not happen until she's what, a בוגרת? Bogeret?
Yeah, or a נערה. Na'arah. Now it could happen, it's legally still
allowed, but the גמרא Gemara is now—is now trying to prevent it.
saying the father and the daughter have the right to say no,
and now it's even saying you should say no, you shouldn't do
it. Okay. אין פוסקין על הקטנה להשיאה כשהיא קטנה. Ein poskin al
haktana lehasio k'she hi ktana. You do not make an arrangement to
marry the girl off, do the נישואין nissu'in while she's still a
קטנה. ktana. אבל פוסקין על הקטנה להשיאה כשהיא גדולה, Aval poskin al
haktana lehasio k'she hi gedola, but you can make an arrangement, presumably
the father, while she's a
קטנה ktana that the נישואין nissu'in will happen once she becomes an
adult, once she's a נערה na'ara after בת מצוה. Bas Mitzvah. To
a Sunday בת מצוה, Bas Mitzvah, Monday wedding. Okay, פשיטא, Pshita, the
גמרא Gemara says obviously. No, מהו דתימא ליחוש דילמא מיפחדא מהשתא וחלשה.
Ma'u d'teima lichosh dilma mifchada me'hashta v'chalsha. Obviously
you can arrange for the נישואין nissu'in after she's a קטנה. ktana.
גמרא Gemara says no, maybe you shouldn't even arrange for it now
while she's a קטנה ktana even though the date is set for
later because now she's a קטנה ktana and you're telling her, 'Hey
honey, in a year after your בת מצוה Bas Mitzvah you're going
to get married to this guy.' So she's now very afraid, she's
still 11 years old or 10 years old, so to even be
planning it might not be a good idea. So the גמרא Gemara
says דילמא מיפחדא מהשתא, dilma mifchada me'hashta, now she has fear, וחלשה,
v'chalsha, and she grows despondent or despairing. קא משמע לן Ka mashma
lan that we're not concerned about that. Okay, but now we've introduced
the idea that you do not, you're entitled to object to נישואין
nissu'in during that and actually you should object to נישואין, nissu'in, you
should not do נישואין nissu'in while she is a קטנה. ktana. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, says
רב הונא, Rav Huna, בוגרת יום אחד ונתקדשה נותנין לה שלשים יום
כאלמנה, Bogeres yom echad v'nis'kadsha nosnin la shloshim yom k'almana, that once
the woman hits בגרות, bagrus, 12 and a half, and there has
been קידושין, kiddushin, then she does not have 12 more months anymore.
Then if there's been קידושין kiddushin and she hits בגרות, bagrus, now
she's the old age of 12 and a half, that's when you're
expected to get married. Then you only have 30 days. So the
גמרא Gemara says מיתיבי, Meisive, I'll ask you on this, בוגרת הרי
היא כתבעוה. Bogeres harei hi k'tavu'ha. Once a woman hits בגרות, bagrus,
it's the husband said it's time to get married. Now once he
says it's time to get married you have 12 months. מאי לאו,
Mai lav, does that not mean כתבעוה דבתולה, k'tavu'ha d'besula, when a
case of a
בתולה besula and he said it's time to get married that there's
12 months. So once she hits בגרות bagrus it's also 12 months
even if he didn't demand it. לא, Lo, no, כתבעוה דאלמנה, k'tavu'ha
d'almana, it's when he demands it from an אלמנה almana where it's
30 days.
Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara going to reject this.
תא שמע, Ta shma, come and hear. בוגרת ששהתה שנים עשר חודש,
Bogeres she-shasta shneim asar chodesh,
a woman hit בגרות bagrus 12 and a half and now it's
been 12 months and it sounds like the husband did not demand
the wedding, it's just been 12 months since בגרות. bagrus. רבי אליעזר
אומר הואיל וחייב בעלה במזונותיה יפר, Rabbi Eliezer omer ho'il v'chayav ba'ala
b'mezonoseha yafer,
since the husband is now obligated to feed her because the 12
months are up, יפר, yafer, he can annul her vows. So anyway,
we're not interested in the vows, what we are interested in, 12
months after בגרות bagrus he's obligated to feed her, which means that's
when they should be getting married, 12 months, not 30 days, 12
months. The גמרא Gemara says אימא בוגרת ושהתה שנים עשר חודש, Eima
bogeres v'she-shasta shneim asar chodesh,
change the גרסא. girsa. Have it read a בוגרת, bogeres, meaning a
woman who's hit בגרות bagrus and it's been 30 days, or a
case of 12 months, but not a case of בוגרת. bogeres. רבי
אליעזר אומר הואיל ובעלה חייב במזונותיה
יפר. Rabbi Eliezer omer ho'il u'ba'ala chayav b'mezonoseha yafer. Again, not at
all פשט. pshat. Don't worry, we're going to reject it. תא שמע,
Ta shma, come and hear. המארס את הבתולה, Ha-m'ares es ha-besula,
a woman who does אירוסין, eirusin, a man who is מארס, m'ares,
does אירוסין eirusin with a woman. בין שתבעה הבעל והיא מעכבת, Bein
she-tva'ah ha-ba'al v'hi m'akeves,
whether the husband was the one who said time to get married
and she's the one that said one minute I need some time,
so then we're going to give her 12 months. בין שתבעה היא,
Bein she-tva'ah hi, and now we're finding out that actually it did
occur that the woman was able to say to the husband, 'Hey
buddy, it's time to do the נישואין.' nissu'in. Okay, and she can
actually pressure him to do the נישואין nissu'in within the time, maybe
she starts wanting to get supported or whatever reason she wants the
נישואין nissu'in to take place. ובעל מעכב, U'ba'al m'akev, and he's postponing.
So this explicates the משנה. Mishnah. Either side after קידושין kiddushin can
say time to do the נישואין nissu'in and then the other side
is given 12 months. נותנין לו שנים עשר חודש משעת תביעה, Nosnin
lo shneim asar chodesh m'shas tvia, you give 12 months from that
moment. אבל לא משעת אירוסין, Aval lo m'shas eirusin, you do not
count it from the time of אירוסין, eirusin, you count it from
the time that one side said it's time to get married.
And now it says, ובוגרת, u-vogeres,
if she hit בגרות, bagrus, הרי היא כתבעוה, harei hi k'tavu'ha, that's
the same as one of the sides demanding that they get married.
כיצד? Keitzad? And then it spells it out. בוגרת יום אחד ונתקדשה,
Bogeres yom echad v'nis'kadsha, she hit בגרות bagrus on one day and
then she had קידושין, kiddushin, נותנין לה שנים עשר חודש, nosnin la
shneim asar chodesh, you give her 12 months. It's explicit. 12 months
from the time she hits בגרות. bagrus. ולארוסה שלשים יום, Ul'arusa shloshim
yom,
and if it's a normal case of an ארוסה arusa 30 days.
We'll see what that means. Let's bracket that for a moment. But
what's important now is it says from the time of בגרות bagrus
you have 12 months, not 30
days, 12 months. תיובתא דרב הונא תיובתא, tyufta d'Rav Huna tyufta,
that is a full contradiction of רב הונא, Rav Huna, you see
that בגרות bagres you have 12 months. מאי ארוסה שלשים יום? mai
arusah shloshim yom? What does it mean for an ארוסה arusah you
have 30 days? So אמר רב פפא הכי קאמר: amar Rav Papa
hachi ka'amar: בוגרת שעברו עליה שנים עשר חודש בבגרות ונתקדשה, bogeres she'avru
aleha shneim asar chodesh b'bagres veniskadsha,
let's say a woman is the old ripe age of 13 and
a half. Okay? She's a בוגרת bogeres and it's been 12 months
before she isn't married yet. She's really getting to be an old
maid. She's 13 and a half. Okay, and now she has קידושין.
kiddushin. In this case, it's בגרות bagres and קידושין, kiddushin, but it's
already a year into בגרות. bagres. So now we gotta get things
moving. You don't want to give her a whole year. In this
case, נותנין לה שלשים יום כאלמנה. notnim lah shloshim yom k'almanah. She
only has 30 days. Which indicates obviously trying to get married right
around that age of 12, 12 and a half, since the clock
starts ticking at בגרות. bagres. Okay, certainly בגרות bagres plus קידושין. kiddushin.
I just want to end by saying first of all we're almost
caught up so we should be very happy. The other point I
just want to say is that תוספות Tosafos points out—one minute to
תוספות—I Tosafos don't get this. If she's a קטנה, ktana, she has
more than 12 months. She can be מעכב m'akev the entire period
she's a קטנה. ktana. If she's a בוגרת, bogeres, the clock starts
ticking right away. So the only case where it's 12 months is
that she's a נערה. na'ara. Okay? Right? Yes? That you need the
guy to demand to get married and that you have 12 months.
If she's a קטנה, ktana, you have more than 12 months. If
she's a בוגרת, bogeres, you don't need to demand to get married.
So the only case of the משנה mishna is that she's a
נערה. na'ara. But if she's a נערה na'ara and he said let's
get married and the clock started ticking, then 6 months later she's
a בוגרת, bogeres, right?
So then that
should you know how does that sort of work in? So תוספות
Tosafos sort of tries to figure the whole thing out about whether
she hits the בגרות bagres after the תבועה tavu'ah or you know
at which stage she's sort of hitting the בגרות. bagres. But
what the גמרא Gemara has basically done is it said קטנה ktana
separate, there it's not a year, there she can basically refuse as
long as she's a קטנה. ktana. And בגרות bagres even without תבועה,
tavu'ah, basically as soon as she hits בגרות bagres the clock starts
ticking. Okay? So the basic scenario in the משנה mishna is that
the תבועה tavu'ah and the clock of the year started when she
was a נערה, na'ara, started in that period between 12 and 12
and a half. Alrighty.
There we go.
Thank you.